<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Milosophical Me (build-deps)</title><link>http://milosophical.me/</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Jan 2015 08:58:44 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Build and install Emacs24 on Debian squeeze</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2012/01/15/build-and-install-emacs24-on-debian-squeeze.html</link><dc:creator>Mike Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Hacking in Debian is so easy (one of the reasons I switched). Take, for instance, building Emacs. This is such a piece of cake compared to the weird hoops you have to go through to get all the build dependencies on other platforms. It's something I never tried before, simply because it was too daunting trying to figure out all the packages I need to install. But apt-get has this awesome --build-deps switch...
&lt;!--more--&gt;

So then, how to build and install Emacs 24 on Debian squeeze, in 6 easy steps?  Since Emacs24 is not yet released, there isn't a package for it in Debian (which is why I'm building my own). But I figured that the build dependencies would not have changed too much from Emacs23, so I used that, and it worked.

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ol&gt;
 &lt;li&gt; Install the build dependencies:
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt; 
   # &lt;strong&gt;apt-get build-dep emacs23&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;
  This installs all the compilers, parsers, development libraries and other parts of the GNU toolchain that is needed to build the emacs23 package.
 &lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt; Download the source code. I used the &lt;a href="https://github.com/emacsmirror/emacs"&gt;GitHub mirror&lt;/a&gt; of the official GNU &lt;a href="http://savannah.gnu.org/projects/emacs/"&gt;Savana codebase&lt;/a&gt;, and downloaded the newest PKzip archive from there.  There is probably a newer one now. Purists probably would check-out direct from either Savana or GitHub rather than download a zip archive... I'm not going to hack emacs itself though, so I don't care.&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt; Unzip the archive and generate the configure script (the autogen step is skipped in the INSTALL file by the way, good thing I've &lt;a href="http://airs.com/ian/configure/configure_3.html#SEC16"&gt;done my homework&lt;/a&gt;):
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
   $ &lt;strong&gt;unzip emacsmirror-emacs-EMACS_PRETEST_24_9_92-295-g2dccfc4.zip&lt;/strong&gt;
   $ &lt;strong&gt;cd emacsmirror-emacssnapshot&lt;/strong&gt;
   $ &lt;strong&gt;./autogen.sh
 &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Follow the INSTALL instructions:&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
   $ &lt;strong&gt;./configure&lt;/strong&gt;
   $ &lt;strong&gt;make&lt;/strong&gt;
 &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;Test it (Note:- if you watch the build, you'll see that after the C core of emacs is built, emacs itself is used to compile the elisp components, so building also makes a fairly good test of the C parts anyway):&lt;br&gt;
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
   $ &lt;strong&gt;src/emacs -Q&lt;/strong&gt;
  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt; If okay, install it:
  &lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;
   # &lt;strong&gt;make install&lt;/strong&gt;
  &lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;br&gt;
 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

</description><category>build-deps</category><category>debian</category><category>emacs</category><category>hacking</category><category>how-to</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2012/01/15/build-and-install-emacs24-on-debian-squeeze.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2012 11:57:54 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>