<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Milosophical Me (Posts about depression)</title><link>http://milosophical.me/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://milosophical.me/tags/depression.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:sinewalker@gmail.com"&gt;Michael Lockhart&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
     src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/80x15.png"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Jul 2018 22:21:36 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>sad-lonely-woman</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2011/sad-lonely-woman.html</link><dc:creator>Michael Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;I rescued some random drunk woman from the gutter (literally) on the way home to the train station this arvo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After using contacts in her phone to try and get some help from friends or family (no one of either category) or neighbors (no answers), I decided to take her home as she said she only lived about a block away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I and another woman bystander helped her home (we used the other woman's car around the corner to get there) and I took her up her steps. Then into the home (she couldn't use keys, took her three goes to find the right set...).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;She slumped to the floor, slipped over backwards just like my little bub does. So, I propped her up with a cushion.  I made sure she was okay to look after herself, got her a glass of water. She seemed only drunk, not stoned (not that I have a lot of experience there...). Left her alone to sober up and sleep it off. As I left she insisted on a hug.  I guess she's okay ? She lives alone with cats, said she'd been drinking vodka, and that she had to go to a job interview (!?) I'm guessing that's why she was out in the street dressed up in a suit jacket. Very sad. Then I missed my train and got home late. So a bit of a downer, really.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you ever feel stressed and lonely and try to get some "Dutch courage" before a job interview through drink, please rethink it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>depression</category><category>mental health</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2011/sad-lonely-woman.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2011 12:11:33 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>