<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Milosophical Me (how-to)</title><link>http://milosophical.me/</link><description></description><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 30 Jan 2015 22:57:21 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Build and install Emacs24 on Debian squeeze</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2012/01/15/build-and-install-emacs24-on-debian-squeeze.html</link><dc:creator>Mike Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hacking in Debian is so easy (one of the reasons I switched). Take, for instance, building Emacs. This is such a piece of cake compared to the weird hoops you have to go through to get all the build dependencies on other platforms. It's something I never tried before, simply because it was too daunting trying to figure out all the packages I need to install. But apt-get has this awesome --build-deps switch...

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://milosophical.me/blog/2012/01/15/build-and-install-emacs24-on-debian-squeeze.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>build-deps</category><category>debian</category><category>emacs</category><category>hacking</category><category>how-to</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2012/01/15/build-and-install-emacs24-on-debian-squeeze.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2012 11:57:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Implementing a caching-only DNS on openSUSE</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2010/07/20/implementing-a-caching-only-dns-on-opensuse.html</link><dc:creator>Mike Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Lately I've been noticing significant DNS latency when visiting certain sites. This is most obvious when my browser spends ages with "Looking up some.web.server.com..." in it's status bar. It's particularly bad at sites like &lt;em&gt;wordpress.com&lt;/em&gt; where many pages make reference to sub-domains of wordpress.com and typically also to &lt;em&gt;google.com&lt;/em&gt; for analytics or ads.


While my ISP's DNS infrastructure is pretty good, there are a couple of things I can do to improve DNS look-up, which makes page loads a lot quicker.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

There are two things which can significantly speed up DNS look-ups for your local clients:

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Switch to a faster name service&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Cache your look-ups on your machine, to prevent repeat DNS requests for sites you often visit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

Of course, a combination works well too.



So, what name service do you use? I know of two free/open services that are pretty good and promising to get better:

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="OpenDNS" href="http://www.opendns.com/"&gt;OpenDNS&lt;/a&gt;: This is a globally distributed service that's fairly quick and is free to use. It also offers a simple (and easily bypassed) content filtering service by blocking known domain names&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="Google Public DNS" href="http://code.google.com/speed/public-dns/"&gt;Google Public DNS&lt;/a&gt;: This is a recent service offered by Google as an experiment in DNS technologies. Again it's globally distributed (using any-cast so the same IP routes to the Google data centre closest to you). No filtering is provided&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

Both are great services. &lt;a title="Unixmen: Google vs OpenDNS" href="http://www.unixmen.com/news-today/612-opendns-vs-google-dns"&gt;Performance varies depending on where in the world you are&lt;/a&gt;.  Since I'm in Australia, Google beats OpenDNS, but I'm going to use both of these and my ISP since it's still fairly good too.

&lt;h2&gt;Hack 0: install and configure BIND&lt;/h2&gt;

In openSUSE, you can install &lt;a title="(Wikipedia)" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/BIND"&gt;bind&lt;/a&gt; like this (as root):

&lt;pre style="padding-left:30px;"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# &lt;strong&gt;zypper install bind&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

Although the program is called &lt;a title="Internet Systems Consortium's page about BIND" href="http://www.isc.org/software/bind"&gt;BIND&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title="Off-topic: interesting diversion in application of use-mention in various fields. It comes up quite a lot in computers :)" href="http://www.google.com/search?q=%22the+name+of+the+song%22+haddocks+eyes"&gt;the name of the service is&lt;/a&gt; actually &lt;a title="TLDP, NAG2, Running named" href="http://tldp.org/LDP/nag2/x-087-2-resolv.named.html"&gt;named&lt;/a&gt; (name daemon). It's configured with the file &lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;/etc/named.conf&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. Edit this (as root) to add a list of up to three forwarding DNS name servers. I'm going with Google as Primary, then OpenDNS, then my router (which forwards to my ISP):

&lt;pre style="padding-left:30px;"&gt;&lt;code&gt;forwarders { 8.8.4.4; 208.67.222.222; 16.1.1.1; };

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

Next, you need to tell openSUSE to start the DNS server at boot time. It makes sense to have it running whenever there are network services. In openSUSE, this means at &lt;a title="(Wikipedia) - what's a runlevel" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Runlevel"&gt;runlevels&lt;/a&gt; 3 and 5. I use &lt;a title="Yet another Setup Tool - the reason I still run openSUSE" href="http://chorgan.provo.novell.com/yast/doc/SL11.1/"&gt;YaST&lt;/a&gt; because it's so simple:

&lt;pre style="padding-left:30px;"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# &lt;strong&gt;yast2 runlevel&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

Finally, start the server. Either do it from YaST, or with the command-line:

&lt;pre style="padding-left:30px;"&gt;&lt;code&gt;# &lt;strong&gt;service named start&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;Hack 1: local resolver&lt;/h2&gt;

This is simple: add the nameserver addresses to your &lt;code&gt;&lt;strong&gt;/etc/resolv.conf&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/code&gt;, like so:

&lt;pre style="padding-left:30px;"&gt;&lt;code&gt;nameserver 127.0.0.1      # Localhost bind

nameserver 8.8.4.4        # Google

nameserver 208.67.222.222 # OpenDNS

nameserver 16.1.1.1       # My router (forwards requests to my ISP)

&lt;/code&gt;

&lt;/pre&gt;

There are alternate addresses for each of Google and OpenDNS, I've chosen one each above. The other addresses are &lt;strong&gt;8.8.8.8&lt;/strong&gt; for Google, and &lt;strong&gt;208.67.220.220&lt;/strong&gt; for OpenDNS. OpenDNS also offers "family shield" on &lt;strong&gt;.123&lt;/strong&gt; but your teenager (or maybe your six-year-old?)  can bypass that pretty easily.

&lt;h2&gt;Other computers&lt;/h2&gt;

Now, any time your browser makes a DNS look-up, the resolv.conf tells it to try your local DNS server first, which in turn forwards to Google, OpenDNS and the router, and caches the results for next time.



If you want other machines in your house to use this name server, &lt;a title="Configuring nameservers for different operating systems - use your own address instead of FamilyShield" href="https://store.opendns.com/familyshield/setup/computer"&gt;just configure them&lt;/a&gt;. If you point their primary DNS server at your openSUSE box's address, they will use the same named you just configured.</description><category>DNS</category><category>hacking</category><category>how-to</category><category>openSUSE</category><category>public DNS</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2010/07/20/implementing-a-caching-only-dns-on-opensuse.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 20 Jul 2010 01:07:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>What happened to my Ctrl-+/- zoom in Xorg?</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2010/07/09/what-happened-to-my-ctrl-zoom-in-xorg.html</link><dc:creator>Mike Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Older X.org and XFree86 used to have this neat feature where pressing Ctrl+&amp;lt;numpad +&amp;gt; and Ctrl+&amp;lt;numpad -&amp;gt; would cycle through the screen modes defined in your config file in the "Screen" section, effectively switching screen modes on the fly and letting you pan around the full virtual screen size with the mouse.


This was a really useful feature for zooming in on small details, or to blow up videos without incurring high CPU overhead.



But since about X.org 1.7 this feature seems to be missing.  I've been researching and discovered why it's missing, and what to do about it.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;So why is it missing?&lt;/h2&gt;

It's part of an architecture change in X.org and Linux, to support screen-mode switching for suspend/resume on laptop computers and a few other stability problems and useability things. Also it has something to do with the "kvm" module in the Linux kernel I &lt;em&gt;think&lt;/em&gt;.  (KVM doesn't work with my Radeon driver, at least not the version included in openSUSE 11.2, yet openSUSE has it enabled by default in 11.2, but that's another story).

&lt;h2&gt;What can I do about it?&lt;/h2&gt;

You can look into screen magnifying software to make parts of the screen larger. Ew! (The whole point of switching screen mode is that the monitor does the magnification in hardware, rather than using the CPU or the GPU, so I can watch YouTube full-screen without the CPU having to multiply the pixels)



Alternatively this functionality is replaced by the new &lt;a title="(Wikipedia)" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/XRandR"&gt;XRandR&lt;/a&gt; extension to X11. You can list the modes defined for your system, as well as the status of all your screens connected to your card with the command-line tool &lt;code&gt;&lt;strong&gt;xrandr&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/code&gt;:

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;

[~]archimedes$ &lt;strong&gt;xrandr&lt;/strong&gt;

Screen 0: minimum 320 x 200, current 1280 x 1024, maximum 3840 x 1200

VGA-0 disconnected (normal left inverted right x axis y axis)

&lt;em&gt;DVI-0&lt;/em&gt; connected 1280x1024+0+0 (normal left inverted right x axis y axis) 338mm x 270mm panning 1280x1024+0+0
   &lt;em&gt;1280x1024&lt;/em&gt;      60.0*+   75.0     60.0*
   &lt;em&gt;1152x864&lt;/em&gt;       75.0
   &lt;em&gt;1024x768&lt;/em&gt;       75.0     70.1     60.0
   &lt;em&gt;832x624&lt;/em&gt;        74.6
   &lt;em&gt;800x600&lt;/em&gt;        72.2     75.0     60.3     56.2
   &lt;em&gt;640x480&lt;/em&gt;        75.0     72.8     66.7     59.9
   &lt;em&gt;720x400&lt;/em&gt;        70.1
S-video disconnected (normal left inverted right x axis y axis)



&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

So from above info I can see:

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;My LCDs native resolution is 1280x1024&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;This screen is identified as "DVI-0" to xrandr&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;The 1280x1024 mode is set as the Preferred mode (marked with a +) which makes sense because it matches the LCD&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;That mode is set as the Current mode (marked with a *)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I have a list of the other modes available, as well as supported refresh rates&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

Now I can change screen mode like this:

&lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;xrandr --output DVI-0 --mode 800x600 --panning 1280x1024&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

That keeps the virtual screen at the same size but the actual display mode is 800x600 (without the --panning switch, the virtual screen size changes to match the mode, which isn't fun really).  I can switch back with:

&lt;p style="text-align:center;"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;code&gt;xrandr --output DVI-0 --mode 1280x1024 --panning 1280x1024&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

Now all that remains is to bind these commands to keyboard shortcuts. The way to do that depends on the desktop environment you use. I'm still looking into how to do it for KDE and / or Awesome.



Oh, and if I ever plug my screen in via the VGA port, I'd need to change the "DVI-0" to "VGA-0" on my machine.</description><category>XRandR</category><category>hacking</category><category>how-to</category><category>screens</category><category>x11</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2010/07/09/what-happened-to-my-ctrl-zoom-in-xorg.html</guid><pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2010 07:17:58 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Awesome KDE, Java composite hacks</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2010/07/05/awesome-kde-java-composite-hacks.html</link><dc:creator>Mike Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I've been experimenting with the &lt;a title="This is gonna be LEGEN ... wait for it ... DARY" href="http://awesome.naquadah.org/"&gt;awesome&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title="Wikipedia" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiling_window_manager"&gt;tiling window manager&lt;/a&gt; as a replacement to KDE's &lt;a title="Wikipedia" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KWin"&gt;kwin&lt;/a&gt;, and I've managed to hack together a recipe for getting them up an running. It's surprisingly simple, although the learing curve was a little steep.


This post documents what I've done to get things working nicely with the basic awesome config. No customisations here, see the &lt;a title="Awesome's wiki" href="http://awesome.naquadah.org/wiki/Main_Page"&gt;awesome wiki&lt;/a&gt; for some &lt;a title="Customising Awesome" href="http://awesome.naquadah.org/wiki/Main_Page#Customization"&gt;ideas&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h2&gt;Rationale&lt;/h2&gt;

After living in emacs for a few years I've come to appreciate it's &lt;a title="What's LCARS?" href="http://memory-alpha.org/wiki/LCARS"&gt;LCARS&lt;/a&gt; style of window panels, so I started to investigate arranging windows at a more global level in my X desktop. I discovered &lt;a title="Wikipedia" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiling_window_manager"&gt;tiling window managers&lt;/a&gt; and started researching them. I decided I want a light-weight, no-fuss tiling window manager for many reasons, not least being that overlapping windows become a mess, and the computer should really be taking care of arranging windows for me.  So I investigated several, narrowing down to &lt;a title="Written in Haskel, not too bad" href="http://xmonad.org"&gt;xmonad&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title="Window Manager Improved 2" href="http://wmii.suckless.org"&gt;wmii&lt;/a&gt; and finally settling on &lt;a title="This is gonna be LEGEN ... wait for it ... DARY" href="http://awesome.naquadah.org/"&gt;awesome&lt;/a&gt;.



However I still like the general KDE environment with all it's facilities like &lt;a title="The semantic desktop" href="http://nepomuk.semanticdesktop.org/xwiki/bin/view/Main1/"&gt;Nepomuk&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title="Plasma" href="http://plasma.kde.org/"&gt;Plasma&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a title="KDE Desktop COmmunications Protocol" href="http://developer.kde.org/documentation/other/dcop.html"&gt;DCOP&lt;/a&gt;, knotify  integration, &lt;a title="KDE Plasma desktop Run Command" href="http://userbase.kde.org/Plasma/Krunner"&gt;krunner&lt;/a&gt;, hooks to Firefox and the trash can and so on -- all tools I can't live without. So I don't want to give  up KDE altogether just to have a better window manager. What I really want to do is run the KDE environment, but use awesome instead of kwin to manage my windows. If I can keep the eye-candy of transparent windows then that'd be a bonus.



After a week-end of research and hacking, here are my results.

&lt;h2&gt;Installing awesome&lt;/h2&gt;

This is a cinch on openSUSE, and probably also on most distro's.  In openSUSE I just used the &lt;a title="Webpin integrated into Yast" href="http://en.opensuse.org/YaST/Research/YaST_Interface_for_Webpin"&gt;Webpin&lt;/a&gt; module in YaST to find &lt;a title="awesome packages in the OBS" href="https://build.opensuse.org/search/search"&gt;a package&lt;/a&gt; on the &lt;a title="OpenSUSE Build Service - for end-users, this is akin to Ubunto/Debian Universe" href="https://build.opensuse.org/"&gt;OBS&lt;/a&gt; and then installed that directly from the Webpin module, which added the repository and downloaded and installed the packages for me.



Once installed, this gives an additional Session type on the kdm login screen, which is neat for testing or using awesome by itself, but when you launch KDE it's still the same (as you would expect!)

&lt;h2&gt;Replacing the KDE window manager&lt;/h2&gt;

After some searching on a few forums I found that KDE's window manager can be set by putting the following into a script in the per-user KDE environment directory (&lt;code&gt;~/.kde4/env&lt;/code&gt; for KDE4)

&lt;p style="padding-left:30px;"&gt;&lt;code&gt;KDEWM=/usr/bin/awesome&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

This has the advantage that it only affects you, not everyone on the system who runs KDE.  Also it's easy to turn off and get the original kwin back if you want to.  I may look into adding KDE+awesome as a session type and then having a separate section in my &lt;code&gt;~/.xinitrc&lt;/code&gt; in the future if I'll be swapping back more often.  I don't anticipate it today though.

&lt;h2&gt;Fixing Java&lt;/h2&gt;

There is a &lt;a title="Java reparinting window bug" href="http://bugs.sun.com/bugdatabase/view_bug.do?bug_id=6429775"&gt;bug&lt;/a&gt; in Java 1.5 and 1.6 where it makes protocol assumptions that are not true in non-reparanting window managers (something along those lines anyway).  It results in Java GUIs appearing as just a grey box in certain window managers like xgl, dwm, wmii, xmonad and awesome. &lt;a title="awesome tip to fix grey Java windows" href="http://awesome.naquadah.org/wiki/Problems_with_Java"&gt;Apparently&lt;/a&gt; this'll be fixed in Java 1.7. In the mean-time, to fix it for 1.5 and 1.6 you can install a utility called &lt;a title="wmname" href="http://tools.suckless.org/wmname"&gt;wmname&lt;/a&gt; (I used Webpin again) and then put this in a script to run at start-up (i.e. in &lt;code&gt;~/.kde4/Autostart&lt;/code&gt;)

&lt;pre style="padding-left:30px;"&gt;&lt;code&gt;#!/bin/sh

/usr/bin/wmname LG3D

&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

The "LG3D" window manager name above is one of the strings that 1.5 and 1.6 JVMs look for and change their behavior if found. This value is the name of the&lt;a title="Wikipedia" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project_Looking_Glass"&gt; LookingGlass3D&lt;/a&gt; window manager, by Sun. Appreciate the irony...

&lt;h2&gt;Composite effects (transparency and shadows)&lt;/h2&gt;

I found &lt;a title="explains xcompmgr and setting it up" href="http://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Xcompmgr"&gt;this link&lt;/a&gt; on the ArchLinux wiki. It's very useful and describes how to enable &lt;a title="Enabling composite extension in Xorg 7.1+" href="http://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Composite"&gt;composite&lt;/a&gt; effects by default in your Xorg, and includes a &lt;a title="start/stop xcompmgr" href="http://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Xcompmgr#Starting.2FStopping_xcompmgr_on_Demand"&gt;script&lt;/a&gt; to turn effects on and off (quite useful on my aging AthlonXP  + Radeon, which can &lt;em&gt;only just&lt;/em&gt; handle the effects, but works nice and snappy without them).



With all this done I have a nice stable and useful desktop which I can begin to tweak when I get a chance to play with the Lua language that Awesome is configured with. More toys to play with :)</description><category>KDE</category><category>awesome</category><category>desktop</category><category>geek</category><category>hacking</category><category>how-to</category><category>useability</category><category>xcompmgr</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2010/07/05/awesome-kde-java-composite-hacks.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2010 04:54:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>MS-Windows focus-follows-mouse Registry hacks</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2010/03/10/ms-windows-focus-follows-mouse-registry-hacks.html</link><dc:creator>Mike Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I like the "focus follows mouse" window-focussing model from X11, because
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I don't have to click on the window, just move the mouse and the window it's over is focussed&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I can focus a window &lt;em&gt;without&lt;/em&gt; bringing it to the front, which is sometimes handy. If I want it in front, I can click it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

However MS-Windows follows the old-fashioned, Macintosh/Smalltalk style of having users click on a window to focus it for the keyboard. How do you make MS-Windows behave more like X11?



&lt;!--more--&gt;I used to install &lt;strong&gt;TweakUI &lt;/strong&gt;from Microsoft, just so that I could turn on an X11-like focus-follows-mouse mode, but Microsoft don't make TweakUI for Vista (there is &lt;strong&gt;TweakVI &lt;/strong&gt;instead, if you want to Google for it. It's by some other company. It's not bad, but overkill for what I want to do).



In Vista, Microsoft added a GUI for this mode that's &lt;em&gt;almost&lt;/em&gt; what I want. You can do this:



Open Control Panel (new view, not Classic)

&lt;p style="padding-left:30px;"&gt;&amp;gt; Ease of Access Center&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="padding-left:60px;"&gt;&amp;gt; Make the mouse easier to use&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p style="padding-left:90px;"&gt;&amp;gt; [ ] Activate a window by hovering over it with the mouse&lt;/p&gt;

But this also brings the window to the front when it's focussed.  If that's what you want, then you're done. If you're like me and you want the window under the mouse to have keyboard focus, but you &lt;em&gt;don't&lt;/em&gt; want it brought to the front without clicking on it, you'll need to hack the Windows Registry. Here are some steps, which should be good for any release of Windows that is based on Windows NT (NT, 2000, XP, Vista, Win7):

&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Run &lt;strong&gt;regedit &lt;/strong&gt;(Win+R, regedit, OK)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Open up the key &lt;strong&gt;HKEY_CURRENT_USER\Control Panel\Mouse&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Change the value of the REG_DWORD &lt;strong&gt;ActiveWindowTracking&lt;/strong&gt; to 0x0000001 (1)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Open up the key &lt;strong&gt;HKEY_CURRENT_USER\Control Panel\Desktop&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Logical OR&lt;/strong&gt; the first byte of the REG_BINARY &lt;strong&gt;UserPreferencesMask&lt;/strong&gt; with &lt;strong&gt;0&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1&lt;/strong&gt;.  That is, if the current value is df 3e 03 80 12 00 00 00, then leave the 'df' alone. If it's 9&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;e&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; 03 07 80 12 00 00 00 , change it to 9&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;f&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/strong&gt;.. ..  and so on &lt;strong style="color:#7744ee;"&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;To make the focus a little slower, so that pop-up windows are useable, you also want to change the focus timing. Change the REG_DWORD &lt;strong&gt;ActiveWindTrkTimeout&lt;/strong&gt; (also in HKEY_CURRENT_USER\Control Panel\Desktop) to the number of milliseconds to wait before focus shifts to the window under the mouse.  I like a value of 0x00000080 (128ms). You might like 200ms (c8), or some faster or slower value.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;strong style="color:#7744ee;"&gt;*&lt;/strong&gt; If you can't do this hexadecimal bit twiddling math in your head (difficult if you're not a programmer), then Windows' Calc can do it for you: put it in Programmer and Hex modes, type the first byte (hex pair e.g. 9e), press the 'Or' button, then '1' and the '=' button.  If the number changes, that's what you replace the first byte with. Thanks to Erik in the comments below, I've finally figured this out and (I hope) clarified what to do..



So, in summary, the Registry keys are as follows for X11-like window focus:

&lt;pre&gt;HKEY_CURRENT_USERS\Control Panel\Mouse

  REG_DWORD ActiveWindowTracking = 0x00000001  (1)

HKEY_CURRENT_USERS\Control Panel\Desktop

  REG_DWORD ActiveWindTrkTimeout = 0x00000080  (128)

  REG_BINARY UserPreferencesMask OR= 01 .. .. .. .. .. .. .. ..&lt;/pre&gt;

These registry hacks require a reboot to take effect.</description><category>desktop</category><category>geek</category><category>hacking</category><category>how-to</category><category>tip</category><category>useability</category><category>windows</category><category>x11</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2010/03/10/ms-windows-focus-follows-mouse-registry-hacks.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 10 Mar 2010 03:42:26 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Essentials to make Windows almost bareable</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2007/06/07/essential-tools-to-make-windows-almost-bareable.html</link><dc:creator>Mike Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Okay, so I hate working in Windows, but on my employer's equipment at least, I must live with it. After having had this machine replaced twice (faulty Dell hardware) and rebuilt more times than I can remember (Windows BSODs), for a total of at least 3 system migrations this past year, I thought I'd better keep a list of what free software to install on top of Windows, and what adjustments to make, so that at least I don't feel like I'm wearing a straight jacket.  Here goes:


&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;/p&gt;&lt;h3&gt;Useability&lt;/h3&gt;

Fix the keyboard to &lt;a href="http://sinewalker.wordpress.com/2006/03/27/dvorak-keyboards/"&gt;Dvorak&lt;/a&gt; (following is for Windows XP -- this will likely change for Vista... it shouldn't be this complicated!)

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Open Control Panel:  &lt;strong&gt;START &amp;gt; Control Panel&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Choose "&lt;strong&gt;Regional and Language Options&lt;/strong&gt;" (why not Keyboard???)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Select "&lt;strong&gt;Languages&lt;/strong&gt;" tab, press Details... button (sigh)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In the "&lt;strong&gt;Installed services&lt;/strong&gt;" section, select "&lt;strong&gt;Keyboard&lt;/strong&gt;", then press "&lt;strong&gt;Add...&lt;/strong&gt;" to add a new keyboard layout&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Find &lt;strong&gt;US-Dvorak&lt;/strong&gt; in the list&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In the "&lt;strong&gt;Default input language&lt;/strong&gt;" section, set the default language to English (Australia) - United States-Dvorak&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In the "&lt;strong&gt;Preferences&lt;/strong&gt;" section, press "&lt;strong&gt;Language Bar...&lt;/strong&gt;" button&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Make sure that "&lt;strong&gt;Show the language bar on the desktop&lt;/strong&gt;" is turned &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;on&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, to make it easier to switch to QWERTY if needed&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Back in "&lt;strong&gt;Preferences&lt;/strong&gt;", press the "&lt;strong&gt;Key Settings...&lt;/strong&gt;" button&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Turn &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;off &lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;all the language &lt;strong&gt;Hot keys&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

To get rid of that &lt;a href="http://www.winsupersite.com/images/showcase/xp_n_05.jpg"&gt;horrible&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://www.winsupersite.com/images/showcase/xp_n_03.jpg"&gt;garish &lt;/a&gt;blue/green stock XP theme, I use the &lt;a title="Zune -- it's still Microsoft, but it looks less garish" href="http://stevenharman.net/blog/archive/2006/12/09/WinXP__Zune_Theme.aspx"&gt;Zune theme&lt;/a&gt; from Microsoft. It sucks less (the theme, that is, not the MP3 player, that sucks &lt;em&gt;more &lt;/em&gt;than iPod).



Make Explorer a bit useable.  Actually Explorer is total crap, and I'm still searching for a replacement. I like &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Midnight_Commander"&gt;MidnightCommander&lt;/a&gt; in Cygwin (&lt;code&gt;mc&lt;/code&gt;), and &lt;a href="http://konqueror.kde.org/"&gt;Konqueror&lt;/a&gt; in KDE.  But for Windows, there aren't a lot of &lt;em&gt;free &lt;/em&gt;Explorer replacements, except maybe Windows File Explorer.  Anyway, follow these steps to have Explorer at least be not so stupid:

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Open an Explorer window (anywhere)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Select "&lt;strong&gt;Tools &amp;gt; Folder Options...&lt;/strong&gt;", "&lt;strong&gt;General&lt;/strong&gt;" tab&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Make sure that under "&lt;strong&gt;Browse folders&lt;/strong&gt;", the option is to "&lt;strong&gt;Open each folder in the same window&lt;/strong&gt;" (Explorer doesn't do multi-windows like Macintosh Finder: it screws them up)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;In "&lt;strong&gt;Click items as follows&lt;/strong&gt;", turn on "&lt;strong&gt;Single-click to open&lt;/strong&gt;", and "&lt;strong&gt;Underline icons only when I point at them&lt;/strong&gt;"&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Select the "&lt;strong&gt;View&lt;/strong&gt;" tab&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Turn &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;on &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;the following:
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;"Display the full path in the address bar"&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;"Display the full path in the title bar"&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;"Do not cache thumbnails"&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;"Show hidden files and folders"&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;"Show both parts and manage them individually" (for web pages and folders)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;"Show encrypted or compressed NTFS files in color"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Turn &lt;em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;off &lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/em&gt;the following:
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;"Hide extensions for known file types"&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;"Launch folder windows in a separate process"&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;"Remember each folder'sview settings"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Press the "&lt;strong&gt;Apply&lt;/strong&gt;", then "&lt;strong&gt;Apply to All Folders&lt;/strong&gt;" buttons&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Press "&lt;strong&gt;OK&lt;/strong&gt;"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Programs&lt;/h3&gt;

Install these programs at a minimum:

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="Rediscover the Web" href="http://en.www.mozilla.com/en/firefox/"&gt;Firefox &lt;/a&gt;(essential add-ons:  &lt;a title="social web bookmarks" href="http://del.icio.us/help/firefox/extension"&gt;del.icio.us&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title="Download Accellerator (and a better manager)" href="http://www.downthemall.net/"&gt;DownThemAll&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title="Spell-check input boxes, in en_au language" href="http://www.justlocal.com.au/clients/oooau/"&gt;English (AU) Dictionary&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title="Block's Flash adds" href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/433"&gt;Flashblock&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title="Make inline images larger" href="http://imagezoom.yellowgorilla.net/"&gt;ImageZoom&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title="Turn on/off proxy settings with one click" href="https://addons.mozilla.org/en-US/firefox/addon/1557"&gt;QuickProxy&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title="Synchronise your local bookmarks between Firefox installations" href="http://www.foxmarks.com"&gt;Foxmarks&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a title="Turn your google mail account into free online storage" href="http://www.getgspace.com/"&gt;GSpace&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="Open Source keystroke starter for Windows" href="http://www.launchy.net"&gt;Launchy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="WFE description page" href="http://www.freesoftlabs.com/fileexpl.asp"&gt;Windows File Explorer&lt;/a&gt; (a free, sort-of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Orthodox_file_manager"&gt;orthodox&lt;/a&gt; file manager for Windows)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="Brings Windows desktop up to status of 1990 Unix" href="http://virt-dimension.sourceforge.net"&gt;Virtual Dimension&lt;/a&gt; (Virtual desktop support for Windows)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="No Machine's Product listing page" href="http://www.nomachine.com/products.php"&gt;No Machine&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;a title="NX Client - Windows - Download" href="http://www.nomachine.com/download-client-windows.php"&gt;NX Client for Windows&lt;/a&gt; (so I can connect a &lt;a title="NX Technology overview" href="http://www.nomachine.com/documentation/intr-technology.php"&gt;high speed X&lt;/a&gt; session to my home machine)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.openoffice.org"&gt;OpenOffice.org&lt;/a&gt; (also use &lt;a href="http://www.justlocal.com.au/clients/oooau/"&gt;JustLocal&lt;/a&gt;'s dictionary / thesaurus files to get spell check working)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="Unix compatibility layer for Windows" href="http://www.cygwin.com/"&gt;Cygwin &lt;/a&gt;(include the X11 modules, Emacs [make sure to select ver 22], pdksh, subversion, python, clisp, fortune, mc, ssh, units, etc....)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://java.sun.com/javase/downloads/index.jsp"&gt;Java SE DevKit&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="Latest Windows Subversion binaries" href="http://subversion.tigris.org/servlets/ProjectDocumentList?folderID=91"&gt;Subversion for Windows&lt;/a&gt; (version control)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.netbeans.org/"&gt;NetBeans&lt;/a&gt; (6.0 or greater has everything I need)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="Audio editor and MP3/OGG converter" href="http://audacity.sourceforge.net/download/windows"&gt;Audacity&lt;/a&gt; audio editor and encoder&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="Network streaming Video" href="http://www.videolan.org/vlc/download-windows.html"&gt;VideoLAN Client&lt;/a&gt; movie player&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.illiminable.com/ogg/"&gt;Illiminable DirectShow filters&lt;/a&gt; for &lt;a href="http://www.vorbis.com/setup_windows/"&gt;OGG Vorbis&lt;/a&gt; (to play .OGG files in Windows Media Player)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="Amiga MOD player" href="http://www.modplug.com/"&gt;MODPlug&lt;/a&gt; (because sometimes a good &lt;a href="http://del.icio.us/sinewalker/modules"&gt;MOD&lt;/a&gt; fits my mood)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="GNU Image Manipulation Program" href="http://gimp-win.sourceforge.net/"&gt;GIMP&lt;/a&gt; image editor&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="Image viewer" href="http://www.irfanview.com/"&gt;IrfanView&lt;/a&gt; image viewer&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3&gt;Emacs&lt;/h3&gt;

Once Cygwin and Emacs are installed, I need to add my dotfiles (from backup), and also install these emacs add-ons:   &lt;a title="Superior Lisp Interaction Mode for Emacs" href="http://common-lisp.net/project/slime/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="Superior Lisp Interaction Mode for Emacs" href="http://common-lisp.net/project/slime/"&gt;SLIME&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/psgml"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/psgml"&gt;PSGML&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a title="Subversion support for Emacs (pre-22)" href="http://www.xsteve.at/prg/emacs/psvn.el"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="Subversion support for Emacs (pre-22)" href="http://www.xsteve.at/prg/emacs/psvn.el"&gt;PSVN&lt;/a&gt; (not strictly needed, since emacs22 adds SVN support in VC mode)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="Collection of Emacs Development Environment Tools" href="http://cedet.sourceforge.net/"&gt;CEDET&lt;/a&gt; (this is not trivial to install, I&lt;em&gt; still &lt;/em&gt;haven't figured it out)&lt;a title="Collection of Emacs Development Environment Tools" href="http://cedet.sourceforge.net/"&gt; &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="Java Development Environment for Emacs" href="http://jdee.sunsite.dk/"&gt;JDEE&lt;/a&gt; (requires some or all of CEDET)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a title="This is neat!" href="http://www.eaflux.com/cygwin/cyg-emacsclient/"&gt;cyg-emacsclient&lt;/a&gt; (wrapper to add Emacs to your SendTo folder, and have it actually work)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

CEDET and JDEE might be more trouble than they're worth, especially since I'm installing NetBeans anyway. They seem cool (especially the enhanced speedbar), but they're not exactly plug-and-play. Jury's still out.</description><category>Delicious</category><category>Microsoft</category><category>cygwin</category><category>dvorak</category><category>emacs</category><category>hacking</category><category>how-to</category><category>jEdit</category><category>java</category><category>lisp</category><category>media</category><category>shell</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2007/06/07/essential-tools-to-make-windows-almost-bareable.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2007 23:16:44 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Remote desktop access on SuSE: Cygwin, X, XDMCP and SSH?  Nope.  FreeNX!</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2007/03/22/remote-desktop-acces-suse-cygwin-x-and-xdmcp.html</link><dc:creator>Mike Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;strong&gt;MJL20080827 -- Update&lt;/strong&gt;:  I Just realised that this is one of my top-visited pages and it's a totally disorganised and incongruent pile of... What's worse is, I've never updated it since the promised update back in March 2007!


Let me clear things up (and save you wading through the whole article): If you want remote access to your openSUSE desktop from a networked thin client, then forget about X11, XDMCP, VNC or tunneling X through SSH. Use the &lt;a title="Nomachine's intro to NX" href="http://nomachine.com/documentation/html/intr-technology.html"&gt;NX&lt;/a&gt; protocol. You'll need to do the following:

&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Install &lt;a title="FreeNX -- an opensource implementation of an NX protocol server" href="http://freenx.berlios.de/"&gt;FreeNX&lt;/a&gt; on your openSUSE host. Some (slightly outdated, but usable) instructions are in Chapter 9 of the &lt;a title="openSUSE 10.2 Reference manual (PDF)" href="http://www.novell.com/documentation/opensuse102/pdfdoc/opensuse102_reference/opensuse102_reference.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;openSUSE 10.2 Reference manual&lt;/a&gt;. If you're using openSUSE 11.0 or newer, &lt;a title="FreeNX" href="http://software.opensuse.org/search?baseproject=openSUSE%3A11.0&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;q=FreeNX"&gt;get the latest FreeNX package&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a title="All about openSUSE Build Service" href="http://build.opensuse.org/"&gt;openSUSE Build Service&lt;/a&gt; (there are &lt;a title="openSUSE one-click install standard" href="http://en.opensuse.org/Standards/One_Click_Install"&gt;one-click install&lt;/a&gt; buttons)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Install an NX client on your remote terminal(s). &lt;a title="Nomachine home page" href="http://www.nomachine.com/"&gt;Nomachine&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a title="Nomachine's downloads page" href="http://www.nomachine.com/download.php"&gt;free NX clients&lt;/a&gt; for Linux, Mac, Windows and Solaris (even some experimental ones for PlayStation 2 and Zaurus!). If your remote terminal is running openSUSE, you could alternatively &lt;a title="Free NX client from OBS" href="http://software.opensuse.org/search?baseproject=openSUSE%3A11.0&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;q=freenx-client"&gt;get an open-source NX client&lt;/a&gt; from the build service (or ask yourself: I'm running X locally, so why don't I just use good ole SSH and X11?)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Configure your NX client to connect to the openSUSE host, then log in and enjoy!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;The upshot: &lt;/strong&gt;I've done this with a FreeNX server and Nomachine's NX client for Windows XP, and it all "just works", except maybe for some font issues with older X clients like emacs (install extra font packages from nomachine to fix that), and some transparency effect issues I noticed in kwin4, probably to do with X11 extensions missing in the NX client. Not a big deal.



Read the rest of this article for the boring background and laughable false-starts in my quest for remote desktops in X... &amp;lt;blush/&amp;gt;



&lt;!--more--&gt;



...



What I would &lt;em&gt;really &lt;/em&gt;love to be able to do is get a graphical log-in screen to my openSUSE box, and have the &lt;a title="KDE Screenshots (Google)" href="http://images.google.com.au/images?q=kde%20screenshot&amp;amp;ie=UTF-8&amp;amp;oe=UTF-8&amp;amp;aq=t&amp;amp;rls=org.mozilla:en-US:official&amp;amp;client=firefox-a&amp;amp;um=1&amp;amp;sa=N&amp;amp;tab=wi"&gt;KDE &lt;/a&gt;environment displayed onto a single window within the WinXP desktop on the notebook (sort of like Windows' Remote Desktop feature &lt;code&gt;mstsc.exe&lt;/code&gt;, or the original &lt;a title="X Terminal (Wikipedia)" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/X_terminal"&gt;X Terminals&lt;/a&gt; we used when I was a student at &lt;a title="School of Computing, University of Tasmania" href="http://www.comp.utas.edu.au"&gt;UTas&lt;/a&gt; back in the nineties).  This way I'd have my full KDE desktop &lt;em&gt;and &lt;/em&gt;it'd be really comfy to use.  So what do I need to do?



Okay, I've finally had enough time at home  to play with connecting to my &lt;a title="openSUSE home" href="http://en.opensuse.org/Welcome_to_openSUSE.org"&gt;openSUSE&lt;/a&gt; box from my work's laptop (WinXP) over my wireless LAN.  It's all groovy:  I can use &lt;a title="PuTTY home" href="http://www.chiark.greenend.org.uk/~sgtatham/putty/"&gt;PuTTY&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a title="Cygwin download mirrors" href="http://cygwin.com/mirrors.html"&gt;Cygwin&lt;/a&gt;'s &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt; command (&lt;code&gt;ssh -Y&lt;/code&gt; to enable X11 tunnelling) to log in, list files, run programs (even X clients, so long as I've started Cygwin's X server first) and it's all secured by an &lt;a title="OpenSSH home" href="http://www.openssh.org/"&gt;SSH&lt;/a&gt; tunnel through the air between my study and my back deck (favorite place to work :-) ).  Note that using &lt;a title="Wireless standard 802.11b (Wikipedia)" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/802.11#802.11g"&gt;802.11g&lt;/a&gt; is probably a little slow for running intensely graphical X clients like photo viewers or &lt;a title="Xaos fractal zoomer home" href="http://wmi.math.u-szeged.hu/xaos/doku.php"&gt;&lt;code&gt;xaos&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/a&gt; ( :-) ), even with a strong signal, but it's good for running an IDE or &lt;a title="Konquerer (Wikipedia)" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Konquerer"&gt;Konquerer&lt;/a&gt;.  And if you add the &lt;code&gt;-C &lt;/code&gt;(Compress) switch to &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt;, it speeds up the intense app's nicely!



Well, obviously I'll need to start X on the WinXP box, without &lt;code&gt;-multiwindow&lt;/code&gt;, and to &lt;code&gt;-query&lt;/code&gt; for an &lt;a title="X Display Manager Control Protocol (Wikipedia)" href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Xdmcp"&gt;XDMCP&lt;/a&gt; server on the openSUSE box.  This should work, since I use a graphical login on openSUSE, which means an XDMCP server is already running (KDM).  So I' tried that, and it doesn't work. Why?



It turns out that nearly every Linux distro' has configured their X display managers (kdm, xdm or gdm) to &lt;em&gt;disable &lt;/em&gt;XDMCP access from external servers and instead only allows connections from &lt;code&gt;localhost&lt;/code&gt; (i.e. from the Linux machine itself).



Why have they done that?  Because XDMCP is insecure:  it transmits passwords in clear.  Also, you cannot secure XDMCP with SSH, as XDMCP uses UDP as well as TCP protocols :-( .  So it's insecure and it cannot be fixed, therefore distribution providers (wisely) disable it.  If I want to have a remote &lt;em&gt;desktop&lt;/em&gt; as opposed to just seeing individual &lt;em&gt;windows&lt;/em&gt; in my Windows desktop (which is cool, but not what I want), then I'll need to either not use SSH and be insecure, or use something else like &lt;a title="Tight VNC -- free VNC server/client" href="http://www.tightvnc.com/"&gt;VNC&lt;/a&gt;.



I'm going to opt for the (insecure) option of not using SSH for X desktop access, and stick to traditional XDMCP sessions.  My reasons for this are:

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I want it to be &lt;em&gt;simple&lt;/em&gt;, and with as little overhead as possible (using VNC involves mucking about with session IDs, or &lt;a href="http://www.linux-mag.com/id/1311?r=s"&gt;running an extra X server on the Linux side&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;I only intend to access my Linux desktop from within my (W)LAN.  I have a firewall in the router, so I can set it to disallow access to ports UDP/177 and TCP/6000 from the Internet (or, if it proves too difficult to do it at the router, I can set openSUSE's own firewall to do that)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;My WLAN is encrypted  over the air anyway (WPA/PSK) and it's also using a silent SSID &lt;em&gt;and &lt;/em&gt;a MAC-address white-list, so it's pretty secure already.  The only way for somebody to sniff out my password is to be physically attached to my router&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;So far I feel I can trust every computer attached to the LAN, since it's my own house.  If (&lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt;?) this changes (that is, once my son is old enough to hack the network, so maybe when he's about eight years old?), I might revisit tunneling XDMCP sessions via VNC through SSH.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

So, how do you set up good ole' XDMCP under Linux? &lt;a title="Linux XDMCP HOWTO (The Linux Documentation Project)" href="http://en.tldp.org/HOWTO/XDMCP-HOWTO/"&gt;READ THE FINE HOW-TO&lt;/a&gt;.  It's that simple, just remember that this is &lt;em&gt;not &lt;/em&gt;secure kids.  If you need security, use VNC, or just &lt;code&gt;ssh -Y&lt;/code&gt; to your Linux host and run individual X clients (with an X server on your local machine). I've also read &lt;a title="Cygwin X-Free mailing list archive" href="http://www.cygwin.com/ml/cygwin-xfree/2004-06/msg00204.html"&gt;in a mailing list&lt;/a&gt; that it's possible to start KDE from an SSH session anyway.  I might give that a go first, since it would be nearly as simple as XDMCP, and also secure.  But I really want my desktop, so we'll see what happens first….



&lt;hr&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 2007-03-26T08:22+1000 Update: &lt;/strong&gt; — Some mixed success



I've learned a couple of things over the week-end:

&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt; ssh -&lt;span style="text-decoration:underline;"&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;Y&lt;/code&gt; (use gzip compression when transmitting packets) produces satisfactory speed for &lt;code&gt;xaos&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;gwenview&lt;/code&gt;, even over my WLAN&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;PuTTY doesn't seem to work any faster, even with Compression Enabled. Perhaps it doesn't support OpenSSL's compression?  I don't know.  Anyway, I don't need PuTTY as long as I have Cygwin with &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;You can start the KDE desktop from an &lt;code&gt;ssh&lt;/code&gt; session with the &lt;code&gt;startkde&lt;/code&gt; command.  However in openSUSE (at least my install) this takes a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; time to start, and eventually &lt;code&gt;kwin&lt;/code&gt; hangs on the notebook end.  On the client end (the openSUSE box), it maxes out the CPU&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

So that was exciting and a little disappointing.  I'll need to experiment a little more it seems.  I got expected warnings about missing font paths and ALSA not working, but I was still hoping to get the desktop up, just with some reduced functionality.  There were also warnings about certain X server extensions being unavailable on the Cygwin X server, which I didn't expect, but again, they aren't critical (no transparency support etc.).  Perhaps there's some environment variables that KDM sets which are causing kwin or other desktop subsystems some grief when missing?



If I still can't get it working soon, I might start with XDMCP, or I might skip straight to VNC after all.  One other thing to try before getting too drastic is to see if the Linux on my notebook's VMWare can run my KDE desktop remotely, or to try booting the notebook from a LiveCD such as Knoppix….



&lt;hr&gt;&lt;strong&gt; 2007-03-29T16:48+1000 Update: &lt;/strong&gt; — RTFM.  Indeed!



It's amazing what you can find out if you just read the manuals that come with your software.  Feeling silly now…I was exploring the &lt;a title="Novell openSUSE Reference manual (PDF)" href="http://milosophical.me/blog/2007/03/22/www.novell.com/documentation/opensuse102/pdfdoc/opensuse102_reference/opensuse102_reference.pdf"&gt;openSUSE Reference manual&lt;/a&gt; on the train home last night. Chapter nine is particularly interesting:  it describes FreeNX, a free remote desktop server, all ready to go on openSUSE, just install and follow the instructions.  There's even an &lt;a title="NX Client for Windows (NoMachine)" href="http://www.nomachine.com/download-client-windows.php"&gt;NX client for Windows&lt;/a&gt;. Much simpler, and still Free.



Looks like this is the way to go.  I'll try it out and do a (hopefully) final  update.</description><category>GUI</category><category>KDE</category><category>Unix</category><category>cygwin</category><category>freenx</category><category>hacking</category><category>how-to</category><category>linux</category><category>nomachine</category><category>nx</category><category>x11</category><category>xorg</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2007/03/22/remote-desktop-acces-suse-cygwin-x-and-xdmcp.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2007 02:59:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Cygwin users and groups</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2006/10/27/cygwin-users-and-groups.html</link><dc:creator>Mike Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;When you first install cygwin and run bash, it'll usually display this error message:
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;Your group is currently "mkpasswd".  This indicates that

the /etc/passwd (and possibly /etc/group) files should be rebuilt.

See the man pages for mkpasswd and mkgroup then, for example, run

mkpasswd -l [-d] &amp;gt; /etc/passwd

mkgroup  -l [-d] &amp;gt; /etc/group

Note that the -d switch is necessary for domain users.&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;If you happen to be in a corporate environment with a huge active directory, then the &lt;code&gt;mkpasswd&lt;/code&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(1)&lt;/sub&gt; command can take a very long time.  A quicker way to fix this issue (provided only the current user uses cygwin on this machine, which is most likely) is to issue this command instead:

&lt;blockquote&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;mkpasswd -l -c &amp;gt; /etc/passwd; mkgroup -l -d &amp;gt; /etc/group&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;/blockquote&gt;

The &lt;code&gt;mkgroup&lt;/code&gt;&lt;sub&gt;(1)&lt;/sub&gt; command will still take a few minutes to complete, but typically there are much fewer groups than users, so it's bearable.</description><category>cygwin</category><category>hacking</category><category>how-to</category><category>tip</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2006/10/27/cygwin-users-and-groups.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 26 Oct 2006 21:47:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Xine performance</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2005/10/31/xine-performance.html</link><dc:creator>Mike Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally published
    at &lt;a href="http://sinewalker.blogspot.com.au/2005_10_01_archive.html"&gt;sinewalker.blogspot.com.au&lt;/a&gt; on 31 October 2005&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now playing with &lt;a href="http://www.gentoo.org/"&gt;Gentoo&lt;/a&gt; as my latest
Linux of choice (I got fed up with RPM dependancy problems, and Gentoo being
source-based solves my other issue with binary-based distributions, where I
felt like a 2nd-class citizen when using or accessing source code).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, I've got &lt;a href="http://xinehq.de/"&gt;Xine&lt;/a&gt; working, but can only use
shared memory for the video decoding.  This is great if I want to capture
screen shots, but not for high-speed movies such as The Matrix, or even just
reading the credits on The Lord of the Ring.  So need to "fix" the performance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I used to have Mandrake
running &lt;a href="http://linuxtv.org/v4lwiki/index.php/Main_Page"&gt;v4l&lt;/a&gt;
+ &lt;a href="http://www.freebsd.org/doc/en_US.ISO8859-1/books/handbook/video-playback.html"&gt;xv&lt;/a&gt;,
but I can't have installed it right in Gentoo because, although xv is loaded,
the performance is glacial if I try to use it.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I
found &lt;a href="http://dvd.sourceforge.net/xine-howto/en_GB/html/howto-9.html"&gt;this
old How-to&lt;/a&gt; with some advice to try... but I might also want to look at
the &lt;a href="http://xinehq.de/index.php/faq"&gt;FAQ&lt;/a&gt;.... probably I haven't
built something into the kernel.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Also while reading around, I
discovered &lt;a href="http://www.mplayerhq.hu/"&gt;Mplayer&lt;/a&gt;.  This looks
like it's worth a download...&lt;/p&gt;

</description><category>DVD</category><category>hacking</category><category>how-to</category><category>tip</category><category>xine</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2005/10/31/xine-performance.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2005 02:43:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>