<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Milosophical Me (Posts about keepassx)</title><link>http://milosophical.me/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://milosophical.me/tags/keepassx.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:sinewalker@gmail.com"&gt;Michael Lockhart&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a rel="license" href="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/"&gt;
&lt;img alt="Creative Commons License" style="border-width:0"
     src="https://i.creativecommons.org/l/by-nc-sa/4.0/80x15.png"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 24 Jun 2018 00:07:07 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Pasword databases: from KeePassX to Unix password store</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2018/keepass-and-password-store.html</link><dc:creator>Michael Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Passwords.  We all have a lot of them to remember — most of us have too many. How do you keep track of them all?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally I used to just remember passwords for everything, like most people.  I soon found this doesn't scale past about 7 passwords and PINs.  Rather than use the same passwords everywhere, I started to keep a secret list of passwords, but it was a pain to keep that list with me, and what if it was discovered?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After been keeping my passwords in a &lt;a href="https://gnupg.org/"&gt;GPG-encrypted&lt;/a&gt; text file for a few years, I then started using a &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/KeePassX"&gt;KeePassX&lt;/a&gt; database, and that's been pretty successful.  I sync the database to my phone so that I can have my passwords with me whenever needed, but it is a little bit clunky to use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the recomendation from someone at work, I checked out &lt;a href="https://www.passwordstore.org/"&gt;pass&lt;/a&gt;, “the standard Unix password manager”.  It offers all the features I've been using from KeePassX for a few years now, only with much better syncronisation based upon git+ssh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pass is also integrated into browsers, editors, and even a few operating systems, so it's potentially a lot less clunky and risky to use than how I was using KeePassX with passwords entered via the system clipboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post reviews my password management approaches to date and gives an overview of Pass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://milosophical.me/blog/2018/keepass-and-password-store.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (9 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>keepassx</category><category>pass</category><category>password-store</category><category>passwords</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2018/keepass-and-password-store.html</guid><pubDate>Sat, 28 Apr 2018 12:52:33 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>