<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Milosophical Me (rant)</title><link>http://milosophical.me/</link><description></description><atom:link type="application/rss+xml" href="http://milosophical.me/tags/rant.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 01:57:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>https://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Java 7 is here - but it's lacking the dolphin's grace</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2011/08/09/java-7-lacking-the-dolphins-grace.html</link><dc:creator>Michael Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, after 5 years and the setting of the Sun, Java SE 1.7 (originally code-named "dolphin") has finally been released. Joyous celebrations from the land of Duke.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://milosophical.me/blog/2011/08/09/java-7-lacking-the-dolphins-grace.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>hacking</category><category>java</category><category>rant</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2011/08/09/java-7-lacking-the-dolphins-grace.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 09 Aug 2011 12:38:54 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Back to openSUSE</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2008/03/31/back-to-opensuse.html</link><dc:creator>Michael Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Well, my stint in *buntu is over, and it ends with an award to openSUSE: this is the first Linux distro I've returned to.


Kubuntu is nice, and I'm happy that I've tried it out, but it's not for me. It's nice enough if you want a simple desktop system, and APT rocks (especially with the aptitude front-end). But it's just not as good as openSUSE, sorry.


&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://milosophical.me/blog/2008/03/31/back-to-opensuse.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (1 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>alternatives</category><category>computers</category><category>hacking</category><category>kubuntu</category><category>observation</category><category>rant</category><category>SUSE</category><category>thoughts</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2008/03/31/back-to-opensuse.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 30 Mar 2008 22:44:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Shifting Interfaces</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2006/03/22/shifting-interfaces.html</link><dc:creator>Michael Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;This post was originally published
  at &lt;a href="http://sinewalker.blogspot.com.au/2006_03_01_archive.html"&gt;sinewalker.blogspot.com.au&lt;/a&gt;
  on 22 March 2006.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once again, Microsoft have &lt;a href="http://www.microsoft.com/office/preview/uioverview.mspx"&gt;drastically changed their Office interface&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
While the new interface is very nice eye-candy and probably has some new features that could help (arguably), it represents yet another need to re-train.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The old argument that &lt;a href="http://www.openoffice.org"&gt;OpenOffice &lt;/a&gt;is too different from &lt;a href="http://office.microsoft.com"&gt;MS-Office&lt;/a&gt; to be quickly useable has just vanished.  &lt;a href="http://www.desktoplinux.com/articles/AT8171250759.html"&gt;OpenOffice is more like MS-Office 97&lt;/a&gt; than MS-Office 2007 will be, and really, who has needed any of the features in Office XP or Office 2003?  What were they, again…?  Oh yeah, anoying interface changes, and removal of the stupid Paperclip.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
I think I'll be distributing my work documents in PDF, created by OOo now, except where I must absolutely use MSO documents for work.  Everthing else will be OOo.  Now I just need to convince my wife that it's not worth continually purchasing MSO, or even having it on our home PC.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>GUI</category><category>Microsoft</category><category>rant</category><category>thoughts</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2006/03/22/shifting-interfaces.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2006 06:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Can't trust the papers…</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2005/11/01/cant-trust-the-papers.html</link><dc:creator>Michael Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally published
    at &lt;a href="http://sinewalker.blogspot.com.au/2005_11_01_archive.html"&gt;sinewalker.blogspot.com.au&lt;/a&gt; on 1 November 2005&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

          &lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;In reference to &lt;a href="http://slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=05/10/31/2247225&amp;amp;tid=188&amp;amp;tid=95"&gt;this Slashdot article&lt;/a&gt; about the Internet killing
  newspapers&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why does "mainstream media" think blogging is such a huge hit? It's not that
Internet is immediate, or that anyone can do it (which has big down-sides as
well as it's egalitarian advantages). It is simply that people everywhere are
fed-up with WWII-era propagandists telling us what to believe and have started
researching it for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is the Information Revolution: the Revolution is greatly improved access
to the information. People are more educated now than they were 50 or even 20
years ago and can make informed judgements. They don't need some "journalist"
to do it for them. This is quite appart form the fact that today's journalism
is extremely poor compared to yester-year's.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I don't buy papers because I know that I can't trust them to bring me news in
an unbiased, non-politically or commercially influenced fashion, or full of
Tabloid rubbish like British newspapers. I accept the risk that the news I
learn via the Net can be from the "uninformed" masses and mitigate this by
using many sources so I can judge for myself where the "truth" lies.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I won't even read over people's shoulders anymore.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
For at least the last 10 years, newspapers have been good for only one thing:
the ink used in newspaper presses is fantastic for removing streaks and smudges
from my computer monitor!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><category>blogging</category><category>media</category><category>rant</category><category>thoughts</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2005/11/01/cant-trust-the-papers.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Nov 2005 04:54:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>“Cyber” security</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2005/10/10/cyberrdquo-security.html</link><dc:creator>Michael Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally published
    at &lt;a href="http://sinewalker.blogspot.com.au/2005_10_01_archive.html"&gt;sinewalker.blogspot.com.au&lt;/a&gt;
    on 10 October 2005&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;hr&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;In reference to &lt;a href="http://it.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=05/10/10/206229&amp;amp;tid=172&amp;amp;tid=103"&gt;this Slashdot article&lt;/a&gt; about U.S. Cybersecurity being about as effectual as FEMA's handling of hurricane Katrina&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I wish USA would stop calling it “cyber security”.  It's just stupid. The word
“cyber” was coined by AI researchers for the ability of computers to interact
with humans, either via a human interface, or by acting human. Later, it turned
more towards embedding computers into humans as a form of prosthetic (a la
“&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/6_Million_Dollar_Man"&gt;$6 millon
man&lt;/a&gt;”) or to build composite computer-humans
(&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cyborg"&gt;cyborg&lt;/a&gt;).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Lately I think the US “cyber security” push has one of these aims:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To control cyborg's access to the net?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To curb “cyberterrorism” — the attack on America by those cyborgs?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;To promote safe use of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Teledildonics"&gt;teledildonics &lt;/a&gt;within federal agencies, a sort of “&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monica_Lewinski"&gt;Monica Lewinsky&lt;/a&gt;” protocol aimed at avoiding future political embarrasments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Obviously, the most likely of these is the third aim… ;-)
&lt;/p&gt;
</description><category>rant</category><category>thoughts</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2005/10/10/cyberrdquo-security.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 10 Oct 2005 11:24:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>RIAA verses the world, and a return to Music Guilds?</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2005/08/31/riaa-verses-the-world-and-a-return-to-music-guilds.html</link><dc:creator>Michael Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;

      &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally published
    at &lt;a href="http://sinewalker.blogspot.com.au/2005_08_01_archive.html"&gt;sinewalker.blogspot.com.au&lt;/a&gt;
    on 31 August 2005&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;In reference to &lt;a href="http://yro.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=05/09/01/0038213&amp;amp;from=rss"&gt;this Slashdot article&lt;/a&gt; about RIAA lawsuits&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seems that RIAA are intent on sueing more 12-year old girls for sharing music... it sickens me.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am not sure what to do to protest (beyond what seems to be happening already
— consumers aren't buying today's crap, and RIAA/ARIA/MPAA etc are just blaming
it on the Net anyway). I am considering what would happen if lots of fans
started writing directly to their favourite artists and asking them these
questions:

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;why do you have this deal with your distributor EMI? I can't play your
  &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;why don't you consider putting sample tracks on your web site? For that matter, why don't you deal directly with Apple, or start your own pay-per-download site for your songs? I'm sure heaps of fans like me will buy them, and you could get a much larger cut per track than Warner Bros is giving you&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Of course, there are costs to running a web site also. But I wonder if what may
happen eventually is a return to music guilds, where a guild runs the site,
member groups contribute content and all proffit goes to the members. It would
probably be a good business to start, atracting new groups like the “Idol” TV
shows do now. Shame I have hopeless business sense though.
&lt;/p&gt;

</description><category>copyright</category><category>media</category><category>rant</category><category>thoughts</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2005/08/31/riaa-verses-the-world-and-a-return-to-music-guilds.html</guid><pubDate>Wed, 31 Aug 2005 04:17:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>