<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"><channel><title>Milosophical Me (Unix)</title><link>http://milosophical.me/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://milosophical.me/tags/unix.xml" type="application/rss+xml" rel="self"></atom:link><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2015 13:18:50 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>http://getnikola.com/</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Old MIT Quotes file</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2011/02/14/old-mit-quotes-file.html</link><dc:creator>Mike Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;em&gt;I found &lt;a title="Just So Quotes" href="http://www.ubiquit.us/retrohomepage/jsq.html"&gt;these quotes&lt;/a&gt; on a random blogger's site, who in turn found this whole file randomly looking through a Terry Pratchett  ftp directory on an MIT machine, back in 1995 or 96. He  luckily saved a copy and I'm reposting here because I don't want to lose them to the fickleness of the Net.&lt;/em&gt;


&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://milosophical.me/blog/2011/02/14/old-mit-quotes-file.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (16 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>C</category><category>MIT</category><category>Unix</category><category>geek</category><category>hacking</category><category>programming</category><category>quotes</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2011/02/14/old-mit-quotes-file.html</guid><pubDate>Mon, 14 Feb 2011 04:37:32 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Kubuntu kaboose</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2007/05/16/kubuntu-kaboose.html</link><dc:creator>Mike Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Yes, I've joined the ubuntu train, and I'm travelling in the Kubuntu car (the caboose?).


This will be, what, my &lt;strong&gt;fifth &lt;/strong&gt;(or sixth if you count Knoppix, but I never put that on my hard drive) Linux distro since trying out RedHat 5.2 back in 1999.  Previous to this I was using openSUSE 10.2 which is not a bad distro either and I always had my eye on SuSE.  So, why yet another distro change?



&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://milosophical.me/blog/2007/05/16/kubuntu-kaboose.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (2 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>KDE</category><category>Unix</category><category>alternatives</category><category>hacking</category><category>kubuntu</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2007/05/16/kubuntu-kaboose.html</guid><pubDate>Tue, 15 May 2007 22:53:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Remote desktop access on SuSE: Cygwin, X, XDMCP and SSH?  Nope.  FreeNX!</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2007/03/22/remote-desktop-acces-suse-cygwin-x-and-xdmcp.html</link><dc:creator>Mike Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MJL20080827 -- Update&lt;/strong&gt;:  I Just realised that this is one of my top-visited pages and it's a totally disorganised and incongruent pile of... What's worse is, I've never updated it since the promised update back in March 2007!


Let me clear things up (and save you wading through the whole article): If you want remote access to your openSUSE desktop from a networked thin client, then forget about X11, XDMCP, VNC or tunneling X through SSH. Use the &lt;a title="Nomachine's intro to NX" href="http://nomachine.com/documentation/html/intr-technology.html"&gt;NX&lt;/a&gt; protocol. You'll need to do the following:

&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Install &lt;a title="FreeNX -- an opensource implementation of an NX protocol server" href="http://freenx.berlios.de/"&gt;FreeNX&lt;/a&gt; on your openSUSE host. Some (slightly outdated, but usable) instructions are in Chapter 9 of the &lt;a title="openSUSE 10.2 Reference manual (PDF)" href="http://www.novell.com/documentation/opensuse102/pdfdoc/opensuse102_reference/opensuse102_reference.pdf" target="_blank"&gt;openSUSE 10.2 Reference manual&lt;/a&gt;. If you're using openSUSE 11.0 or newer, &lt;a title="FreeNX" href="http://software.opensuse.org/search?baseproject=openSUSE%3A11.0&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;q=FreeNX"&gt;get the latest FreeNX package&lt;/a&gt; from the &lt;a title="All about openSUSE Build Service" href="http://build.opensuse.org/"&gt;openSUSE Build Service&lt;/a&gt; (there are &lt;a title="openSUSE one-click install standard" href="http://en.opensuse.org/Standards/One_Click_Install"&gt;one-click install&lt;/a&gt; buttons)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Install an NX client on your remote terminal(s). &lt;a title="Nomachine home page" href="http://www.nomachine.com/"&gt;Nomachine&lt;/a&gt; has &lt;a title="Nomachine's downloads page" href="http://www.nomachine.com/download.php"&gt;free NX clients&lt;/a&gt; for Linux, Mac, Windows and Solaris (even some experimental ones for PlayStation 2 and Zaurus!). If your remote terminal is running openSUSE, you could alternatively &lt;a title="Free NX client from OBS" href="http://software.opensuse.org/search?baseproject=openSUSE%3A11.0&amp;amp;p=1&amp;amp;q=freenx-client"&gt;get an open-source NX client&lt;/a&gt; from the build service (or ask yourself: I'm running X locally, so why don't I just use good ole SSH and X11?)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Configure your NX client to connect to the openSUSE host, then log in and enjoy!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;The upshot: &lt;/strong&gt;I've done this with a FreeNX server and Nomachine's NX client for Windows XP, and it all "just works", except maybe for some font issues with older X clients like emacs (install extra font packages from nomachine to fix that), and some transparency effect issues I noticed in kwin4, probably to do with X11 extensions missing in the NX client. Not a big deal.



Read the rest of this article for the boring background and laughable false-starts in my quest for remote desktops in X... &amp;lt;blush/&amp;gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://milosophical.me/blog/2007/03/22/remote-desktop-acces-suse-cygwin-x-and-xdmcp.html"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (5 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>GUI</category><category>KDE</category><category>Unix</category><category>cygwin</category><category>freenx</category><category>hacking</category><category>how-to</category><category>linux</category><category>nomachine</category><category>nx</category><category>x11</category><category>xorg</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2007/03/22/remote-desktop-acces-suse-cygwin-x-and-xdmcp.html</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Mar 2007 02:59:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Mainframe is process-centred, *nix/windoze is not</title><link>http://milosophical.me/blog/2005/07/18/mainframe-is-process-centred-nixwindoze-is-not.html</link><dc:creator>Mike Lockhart</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was originally published
    at &lt;a href="http://sinewalker.blogspot.com.au/2005_07_01_archive.html"&gt;sinewalker.blogspot.com.au&lt;/a&gt; on 18 July 2005&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;em&gt;In reference
  to &lt;a href="http://ask.slashdot.org/article.pl?sid=05/07/18/2035235&amp;amp;tid=190"&gt;this Slashdot question&lt;/a&gt; about Mainframe Culture&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;    
&lt;p&gt;Appart from the obvious religious stuff about GUI (or lack of) and
user-centred interfaces (or lack of), the biggest difference, and the biggest
advantage that Mainframe brings is it's culture of process and change
control. It is something you should strive to let your Mainframe masters pass
on to the *nix/windoze padawans before they die of old age.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I am a *nix padawan, but, crocky technology asside, I'm frequently impressed by
my Mainframe elders, their ability to deploy code to Production environments
that works *the first time* nearly every time, and their ability to
communictate technical changes necessary to fix broken code in the middle of
the night in the 0.1% of cases where they failed to get it working first time.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Key values that I have picked up from my masters, and which should be
inherrited by both *nix and PC/Mac enclaves are focused around Engineering
principles. Mainframe guru's program like a civil engineer builds a bridge. No
shortcuts are taken unless it can be proven that it is safe to do so. Testing
is carried out in stages and test results must be submitted with the change
request before a program migrates to Production. If a program must “abend”
(Abnormal End) then it should do so noisily and with as much information as
possible. If it finishes cleanly, little information is needed other than this
fact.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
These closely follow the
advice &lt;a href="http://www.catb.org/%7Eesr/"&gt;Raymond&lt;/a&gt; has encoded
in &lt;a href="http://www.catb.org/%7Eesr/writings/taoup/html/"&gt;his book&lt;/a&gt;, but
there is probably much more that your Mainframe gurus know that you should
cherrish and extend to your newer team members.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Forget about the religious wars, the technology changes and the “focus” of your
programmers on users or other programmers. Get the real truth from your
Mainframe masters who have seen it all pass before them but have learned the
hard way how to make a stable computer environment that stays up, even on
cruddy mainframe technology. If their attitudes were adopted by people fluent
in today's fantastic systems, all people would benefit.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The sad fact is that, in today's environment, especially after the dot-com
cowboys set Upper Management expectations, following Process is just too slow,
or too expensive. Convincing management that a bigger cost up front will result
in a lower cost in the long run is also futile when mgt sees it as “normal” for
computer systems to break. After all, their Windows machine on their desk has
been doing that for 20 years now, so it must be normal, right?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
What matters most to managers or clients when deploying new systems these days
seems to be “time to market”, and the only consent to quality is that the IT
dept/company follows check-list processes like CMMI or ISO9000 which do not
address the real issues and put too much into the Process rather than the
Result. Also, when the system breaks, it's typically at the expense of the IT
company that built it, or was stupid enough to agree to use the off-the-shelf
product in the first place, so there is nothing to drive a change of behaviour
from the clients.&lt;/p&gt;

</description><category>Unix</category><category>development</category><category>hacking</category><category>mainframe</category><category>observation</category><category>process</category><category>stability</category><guid>http://milosophical.me/blog/2005/07/18/mainframe-is-process-centred-nixwindoze-is-not.html</guid><pubDate>Sun, 17 Jul 2005 22:52:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>